## George P. Kontoudis

3242 Kim Engineering Building, College Park, MD 20742, USA

★ www.georgekontoudis.com \( \to \) gpkont@vt.edu \( \to \) Updated: January 12, 2022

## **RESEARCH INTERESTS**

My research interests lie in the intersection of robotics, control theory, and machine learning. I am particularly interested in how learning algorithms and control theory can enable multi-agent systems to efficiently collaborate with minimal information exchange for robotic navigation and exploration tasks.

## RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

**INDUSTRY EXPERIENCE** 

Mechanical Engineer, Sychem S.A.

Aircraft Maintenance Engineer Trainee, Olympic Aviation

RESEARCH EATERIEVEE	
Postdoctoral Research Associate (MRC Fellow), University of Maryland Motion and Teaming Lab (PI: Michael Otte)	Jan 2022–present
Graduate Research Assistant, Virginia Tech	
Center for Marine Autonomy & Robotics (PI: Daniel J. Stilwell)	Aug 2018–Dec 2021
Computational Multiphysics Systems Laboratory (PI: Tomonari Furukawa)	Aug 2016–Jul 2018
Undergraduate Research Assistant, National Technical University of Athens	
Control Systems Laboratory (PI: Kostas J. Kyriakopoulos)	Apr 2014–Mar 2016
Founder & Research Associate, OpenBionics	Sep 2014–present
EDUCATION	
PhD in Electrical Engineering, Virginia Tech	2018–2021
Advisor: Daniel J. Stilwell	
Dissertation Title: "Communication-Aware, Scalable Gaussian Processes for Decentralized Explo GPA: 3.94/4.00	oration"
MSc in Mechanical Engineering, Virginia Tech	2016–2018
Advisors: Tomonari Furukawa & Kyriakos G. Vamvoudakis	
Thesis Title: "Adaptive, Anthropomorphic Robot Hands for Grasping and In-Hand Manipulation" GPA: 4.00/4.00	,
Diploma in Mechanical Engineering, National Technical University of Athens	2012–2016
Advisor: Kostas J. Kyriakopoulos	
Thesis Title: "Design and Development of an Underactuated, Anthropomorphic Robot Hand"	
BSc in Mechanical Engineering, University of West Attica	2005–2010
TEACHING EXPERIENCE	
Graduate Teaching Assistant, Virginia Tech	
Department of Mechanical Engineering	Fall 2016, Spring 2017
AWARDS & HONORS	
$5 \times$ IEEE Student Travel Support (IROS, ACC, CDC)	2015, 2019–2021
$2 \times \text{Virginia Tech GSA Travel Fund Award (Humanoids, ICORR)}$	2019, 2020
NSF Student Travel Grant (WuWNet)	2019
NTUA Thomaideion Award	2016
Hackaday Prize, 2 <sup>nd</sup> place among 900 projects	2015
Robotdalen Innovation Award, 1 <sup>st</sup> place	2015

Oct 2010-Aug 2015

May 2008-Jan 2010

### **Referred Journal Publications [J4]**

- [J1] **George P. Kontoudis**, Stephen Krauss, Daniel J. Stilwell, "Model-Based Learning of Underwater Acoustic Communication Performance for Marine Robots," *Robotics and Autonomous Systems*, 2021.
- [J2] Geng Gao, Mojtaba Shahmohammadi, Lucas Gerez, **George P. Kontoudis**, Minas Liarokapis, "On Differential Mechanisms for Underactuated, Lightweight, Adaptive Prosthetic Hands," *Frontiers in Neurorobotics*, 2021.
- [J3] George P. Kontoudis, Kyriakos G. Vamvoudakis, "Kinodynamic Motion Planning with Continuous-Time Q-Learning: An Online, Model-Free, and Safe Navigation Framework," *IEEE Transactions on Neural Networks and Learning Systems*, 2019.
- [J4] George P. Kontoudis, Minas Liarokapis, Kyriakos G. Vamvoudakis, Tomonari Furukawa, "An Adaptive Actuation Mechanism for Anthropomorphic Robot Hands," Frontiers in Robotics and AI, 2019.

## **Referred Conference Publications [C12]**

- [C1] Josh Netter, George P. Kontoudis, Kyriakos G. Vamvoudakis, "Bounded Rational RRT-QX: Multi-Agent Motion Planning in Dynamic Human-Like Environments Using Cognitive Hierarchy and Q-Learning," *IEEE Conference on Decision and Control (CDC)*, Austin, USA, 2021.
- [C2] **George P. Kontoudis**, Daniel J. Stilwell, "Decentralized Nested Gaussian Processes for Multi-Robot Systems," *IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA)*, Xi'an, China, 2021.
- [C3] Minas Liarokapis, **George P. Kontoudis**, "Teaching Robotic and Biomechatronic Concepts with a Gripper Design Project and a Grasping and Manipulation Competition," *IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA)*, Xi'an, China, 2021.
- [C4] **George P. Kontoudis**, Daniel J. Stilwell, "Prediction of Acoustic Communication Performance in Marine Robots Using Model-Based Kriging," *American Control Conference (ACC)*, New Orleans, USA, 2021.
- [C5] Gal Gorjup, **George P. Kontoudis**, Anany Dwivedi, Geng Gao, Saori Matsunaga, Toshisada Mariyama, Bruce MacDonald, and Minas Liarokapis "Combining Programming by Demonstration with Path Optimization and Local Replanning to Facilitate the Execution of Assembly Tasks," *IEEE International Conference on Systems, Man and Cybernetics* (SMC), Toronto, Canada, 2020.
- [C6] George P. Kontoudis, Zirui Xu, Kyriakos G. Vamvoudakis, "Online, Model-Free Motion Planning in Dynamic Environments: An Intermittent, Finite Horizon Approach with Continuous-Time Q-Learning," American Control Conference (ACC), Denver, USA, 2020.
- [C7] George P. Kontoudis, Daniel J. Stilwell, "A Comparison of Kriging and Cokriging for Estimation of Underwater Acoustic Communication Performance," ACM International Conference on Underwater Networks and Systems (WuWNet), Atlanta, USA, 2019.
- [C8] George P. Kontoudis, Minas Liarokapis, Kyriakos G. Vamvoudakis, "An Adaptive, Humanlike Robot Hand with Selective Interdigitation: Towards Robust Grasping and Dexterous, In-Hand Manipulation," *IEEE-RAS International Conference on Humanoid Robots (Humanoids)*, Toronto, Canada, 2019.
- [C9] **George P. Kontoudis**, Minas Liarokapis, Kyriakos G. Vamvoudakis, "A Compliant, Underactuated Finger for Anthropomorphic Hands," *IEEE/RAS-EMBS Inter. Conference on Rehabilitation Robotics (ICORR)*, Toronto, Canada, 2019.
- [C10] **George P. Kontoudis**, Kyriakos G. Vamvoudakis, "Robust Kinodynamic Motion Planning using Model-Free Game-Theoretic Learning," *American Control Conference (ACC)*, Philadelphia, USA, 2019.
- [C11] Kyriakos D. Tsoukalas, George P. Kontoudis, Kyriakos G. Vamvoudakis, "Active-Bayesian Learning for Cooperation Connectivity in Dynamic Cyber-Physical-Human Systems," *IEEE Symposium on Adaptive Dynamic Programming and Reinforcement Learning (ADPRL)*, Honolulu, USA, 2017.
- [C12] George P. Kontoudis, Minas Liarokapis, Agisilaos G. Zisimatos, Christoforos I. Mavrogiannis, Kostas J. Kyriakopoulos, "Open-Source, Anthropomorphic, Underactuated Robot Hands with a Selectively Lockable Differential Mechanism: Towards Affordable Prostheses," IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS), Hamburg, Germany, 2015.

## Theses [T3]

- [T1] **George P. Kontoudis**, "Communication-Aware, Scalable Gaussian Processes for Decentralized Exploration," *Doctoral Dissertation, Virginia Tech*, USA, December 2021.
- [T2] **George P. Kontoudis**, "Adaptive, Anthropomorphic Robot Hands for Grasping and In-Hand Manipulation," *Master Thesis, Virginia Tech*, USA, December 2018.
- [T3] **George P. Kontoudis**, "Design and Development of an Underactuated, Anthropomorphic Robot Hand," *Diploma Thesis, National Technical University of Athens*, March 2016. (in Greek)

## **Technical Reports [R2]**

- [R1] **George P. Kontoudis**, Minas Liarokapis, Agisilaos G. Zisimatos, Christoforos I. Mavrogiannis, Kostas J. Kyriakopoulos, "How to Create Affordable, Anthropomorphic, Light-Weight Prosthetic Hands," *Control Systems Lab, National Technical University of Athens*, Athens, Greece, October 2015.
- [R2] Agisilaos G. Zisimatos, Minas Liarokapis, Christoforos I. Mavrogiannis, **George P. Kontoudis**, Kostas J. Kyriakopoulos, "How to Create Affordable, Modular, Light-Weight, Underactuated, Compliant Robot Hand," *Control Systems Lab, National Technical University of Athens*, Athens, Greece, January 2015.

#### **TALKS & PRESENTATIONS**

- · "Communication-Aware, Scalable Gaussian Processes for Decentralized Exploration" *Bradley Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering, Virginia Tech*, Blacksburg, USA, December 2021. [PhD Defense]
- · "Decentralized Nested Gaussian Processes for Multi-Robot Systems," *IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA)*, Xi'an, China, 2021. [Virtual Presentation]
- · "Online, Model-Free Motion Planning in Dynamic Environments: An Intermittent, Finite Horizon Approach with Continuous-Time Q-Learning," *American Control Conference (ACC)*, Denver, USA, 2020. [Rapid-Interactive Presentation]
- · "A Comparison of Kriging and Cokriging for Estimation of Underwater Acoustic Communication Performance," *ACM International Conference on Underwater Networks and Systems (WuWNet)*, Atlanta, USA, 2019. [Oral Presentation]
- · "An Adaptive, Humanlike Robot Hand with Selective Interdigitation: Towards Robust Grasping and Dexterous, In-Hand Manipulation," Workshop on New Challenges in Humanoid Grasping and Manipulation in IEEE-RAS International Conference on Humanoid Robots (Humanoids), Toronto, Canada, 2019. [Oral Presentation Invited Talk]
- · "An Adaptive, Humanlike Robot Hand with Selective Interdigitation: Towards Robust Grasping and Dexterous, In-Hand Manipulation," *IEEE-RAS International Conference on Humanoid Robots (Humanoids)*, Toronto, Canada, 2019. [Poster Presentation]
- · "Robust Kinodynamic Motion Planning using Model-Free Game-Theoretic Learning," *American Control Conference (ACC)*, Philadelphia, USA, 2019. [Oral Presentation]
- · "A Compliant, Underactuated Finger for Anthropomorphic Hands," *IEEE/RAS-EMBS International Conference on Rehabilitation Robotics (ICORR*), Toronto, Canada, 2019. [Poster Presentation]
- · "Adaptive, Anthropomorphic Robot Hands for Grasping and In-Hand Manipulation," *Department of Mechanical Engineering, Virginia Tech*, Blacksburg, USA, December 2018. [Master's Defense]
- · "Evaluation Strategies of Adaptive, Anthropomorphic Robot Hands for Dexterous In-Hand Manipulation: Early Results," *National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST)*, USA, 2018. [Invited Talk]
- · "Open-Source, Anthropomorphic, Underactuated Robot Hands with a Selectively Lockable Differential Mechanism: Towards Affordable Prostheses," *IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS)*, Hamburg, Germany, 2015. [Oral Presentation]

## SERVICE ACTIVITIES

## **Conference Organizing Committees**

· Online Platform Chair, Conference on Robot Learning (CoRL)

2022

#### Reviewer, Journals

- · IEEE Transactions on Neural Networks and Learning Systems
- · IEEE Transactions on Robotics

· IEEE Transactions on Automation Science and Engineering	2020, 2021
· IEEE Transactions on Cybernetics	2020
· IEEE Transactions on Systems, Man and Cybernetics: Systems	2021
· IEEE Computational Intelligence Magazine	2020
· IEEE Control Systems Letters	2019, 2020
· IEEE Robotics and Automation Letters	2019
· Frontiers in Artificial Intelligence	2021
· Journal of Optimization Theory and Applications	2021
· International Journal of Advanced Robotic Systems	2015, 2016
Reviewer, Conferences	
· American Control Conference (ACC)	2018–2021
· IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA)	2018–2022
· IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS)	2018–2020
· IEEE Conference on Decision and Control (CDC)	2019, 2020
· IEEE International Conference on Automation Science and Engineering (CASE)	2019
· IEEE-RAS International Conference on Humanoid Robots (Humanoids)	2019
IEEE International Conference on Biomedical Robotics and Biomechatronics (BioRob)	2018, 2020, 2021
· European Control Conference (ECC)	2022
· Mediterranean Conference on Control and Automation (MED)	2018
Memberships	
· IEEE, Student Member	2015–present
· ASME, Student Member	2016–present
· SIAM, Student Member	2019–present
MENTORING	
PhD Students	
· Joshua Netter, Georgia Institute of Technology Advisor: Kyriakos G. Vamvoudakis	2020–present

# **Master's Students**

· Zirui Xu, Georgia Institute of Technology

Advisor: Kyriakos G. Vamvoudakis

Currently: PhD student, University of Michigan

## RELEVANT GRADUATE COURSEWORK (VIRGINIA TECH)

Control	AOE5244: Optimization Techniques, AOE5984-SS: Cyber-Physical Systems & Distributed Control, AOE5774: Nonlinear Systems Theory, AOE6544: Linear Control Theory, ME6574: Adaptive Control
	Systems
Robotics	ECE5984-SS: Advanced Robot Motion Planning, ME5984-SS: Advanced Experimental Robotics,
	ME5524: Bayesian Robotics, ECE5984-SS: Autonomous Coordination, ME5984-SS: Motion Planning

ıg Analysis

2018-2020

**Dynamics** AOE5204: Vehicle Dynamics & Control

**Mathematics** MATH5414: Model Reduction of Dynamical Systems, MATH3324: Advanced Calculus

**Others** STAT5544: Spatial Statistics, AOE5984: Scientific Machine Learning & Uncertainty Quantification

ECE5644: Game Theory for Communication Networks